{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man's opinion in Barron v. Baltimore refused to apply Bill of Rights protections to state\ngovernments. He was the target of Andrew Jackson's derisive remark \"now let him enforce it,\"\nand he asserted his Court's power in a case about \"midnight appointments.\" For 10 points, name\nthis Chief Justice whose ruling in Marbury v. Madison asserted the power of judicial review.",
      "answer": "John Marshall, Marshall"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pope Leo I convinced Attila the Hun not to perform this kind of action. This kind of action\nwas done by Gauls following the 390 BC Battle of the Allia. In 410 AD, Alaric led an army of\nVisigoths in performing this action, which St. Jerome identified as the effective end of the\nEmpire. For 10 points, identify this action in which the \"eternal city\" is pillaged.",
      "answer": "sack of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "The formation of this institution triggered the Key West Agreement on its proper usage, which\nwas negotiated on its behalf by its first secretary, Stuart Symington. This organization conducted\nProject Blue Book, a study of UFOs, and it operates Area 51. For 10 points, name this branch of\nthe US military which operates B-52s, F-16s, and other fighter jets.",
      "answer": "United States Air Force, Air Force, USAF"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1970, the concluding game of this event featured the dramatic entrance of an injured Willis\nReed. This event included the \"flu game\" in 1997 and an upset in 2011 that put a championship\nin the hands of Jason Terry, Shawn Marion, and Dirk Nowitski. For 10 points, name this annual\nJune event, which awards the Larry O'Brien trophy to teams such as the Bulls, Heat, or Lakers.",
      "answer": "the NBA Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country's banks, which had been largely taken over by Russian organized criminals by\n2013, underwent a savings account \"haircut.\" This country’s \"enosis\" (pr. ee-NOH-siss)\nmovement propelled Archbishop Makarios to power, sparking an invasion that still divides this\nisland. For 10 points, name this country with Greek and Turkish sectors on an island.",
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This instrument was invented by a Belgian seeking a solution to the problem of clarinets\nraising their pitch when overblown. This instrument was played by Cannonball Adderley as well\nas the composer of Giant Steps, John Coltrane. For 10 points, name this classical and jazz\ninstrument which has alto and tenor varieties and is a woodwind made out of brass.",
      "answer": "saxophone, sax"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1985, this company sued Minolta over the distinctive crossed letters in its logo. This\ncompany is the descendent of Standard Oil of New Jersey, and it employed Joseph Hazelwood,\nwho was accused of being responsible for a 1989 disaster on Prince William Sound. For 10\npoints, name this company whose Valdez tanker caused a huge oil spill, eleven years before it\nmerged with Mobil.",
      "answer": "Exxon, Exxon Mobil Corporation"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first Church council named for this place endorsed ultramontanism and espoused the\ndoctrine of Papal infallibility. The second council named for this place introduced the vernacular\nmass and renounced anti-Semitism. For 10 points, identify this namesake of 1868 and 1962\nCatholic ecumenical councils, which is also the independent state where the Pope lives.",
      "answer": "Vatican, Vatican City"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man refused to continue working on the film The Golden Age after denouncing his\ncollaborator, Luis Buñuel, for \"communism and atheism,\" three years after he completed Un\nChien Andalou (pr. uh shee-EN on-da-LOO) For 10 points, name this Spanish surrealist who\npainted The Persistence of Memory, which shows several melting watches.",
      "answer": "Salvador Dali, Dali"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nobility serving under this dynasty followed the \"Table of Ranks\" to determine bureaucratic\nadvancement. This royal house came to power after three different \"False Dmitris\" were\nsuppressed during the Time of Troubles. For 10 points, name this house founded by Mikhail I in\n1613, which remained in control of Russia until the twentieth century.",
      "answer": "Romanov, Romanov Dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) Whose nomination as Walter Mondale's running mate in 1984 made her the first\nwoman to be a major-party U.S. Vice-Presidential candidate?",
      "answer": "Geraldine Ferraro, Ferraro"
    },
    {
      "question": "The city of Bagram was originally the capital of an ethnically Greek state that practiced this\nreligion. Two statues of this religion's founder at Bamiyan (pr. BAY-mee-yahn) were destroyed\nby the Taliban. For 10 points, name this religion whose Vajryana (pr. VAHJ-rye-AH-nuh) form\nis practiced in Tibet by followers of the Dalai Lama.",
      "answer": "Buddhism"
    },
    {
      "question": "Near the end of his life, this man gave a speech identifying the \"three boxes\" as the source of\nrights. This man was nominated for Vice-President by the Equal Rights Party on the Victoria\nWoodhull ticket. This orator gave a speech asking \"what, to the slave, is the Fourth of July\" after\nfounding The North Star. This author of My Bondage and My Freedom wrote about his escape\nfrom Mr. Covey in Maryland. For 10 points, name this former slave turned abolitionist.",
      "answer": "Frederick Douglass, Douglass"
    },
    {
      "question": "Along with Henry David Thoreau, this thinker was cited as the chief Western influence on\nGandhi. His pacifist tome The Kingdom of God is Within You made him the leader of dissenting\nChristians in early twentieth century Russia. For 10 points, name this man who viewed his\ntheological work as more important than his novels, such as Anna Karenina",
      "answer": "Leo Tolstoy, Tolstoy, Lev Nikolayevich Tolstoy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was set in motion when Abel Corbin introduced its two plotters to the President,\nand Daniel Butterfield agreed to pass along inside information. This 1869 event tainted the Grant\nadministration and was an attempt by James Fisk and Jay Gould to \"corner\" the gold market. For\n10 points, identify this day, which shares its name with a post-Thanksgiving shopping event.",
      "answer": "Black Friday"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king ordered the destruction of all remaining Protestant churches in the Edict of\nFontainebleau (pr. FAHN-tohn-blow). He was opposed at his accession by the Fronde\nmovement, which was countered by his early advisor, Cardinal Mazarin. For 10 points, name this\nmonarch who reigned for seventy-two years as the absolutist \"Sun King\" of France.",
      "answer": "Louis XIV"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man headed the Firebird and GTO projects while he was chief engineer of Pontiac, prior\nto starting his own namesake company. In 1982, he was arrested for participating in a cocaine\ndeal, which he was acquitted of at trial after arguing entrapment. For 10 points, identify this man\nwhose car firm produced a gull-winged, unpainted steel car used in Back to the Future.",
      "answer": "John DeLorean, DeLorean"
    },
    {
      "question": "This party was victimized by the Zinoviev letter hoax, which purported to show Soviet control\nof its operations and brought down its first prime minister, Ramsay Macdonald. This party was\nfirst represented in Parliament by Scottish coal miner Keir Hardie. For 10 points, name this\nparty, now the more left-wing of the two largest political parties in the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": "Labour Party, Labour"
    },
    {
      "question": "Zacharias Janssen may have invented the first version of this device, which was first used in\nbiology by Anton van Leeuwenhoek (pr. LAY-ven-hoke). In 1932, Ernst Ruska pioneered the\n\"electron\" type of this device, which was used to discover cells in cork by Robert Hooke. For 10\npoints, identify this device which lens-grinders created to peer at tiny objects.",
      "answer": "microscope"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's prominent depiction on the cover of When the Word Is Given offended his\nsuperiors, as did his commentary that the John F. Kennedy assassination was \"a case of chickens\ncoming home to roost.\" He was killed at the Audubon Ballroom, most likely by agents of Elijah\nMuhammad. For 10 points, name this chief spokesman for the Nation of Islam.",
      "answer": "Malcom X, Malcolm Little, Little"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the autumn of 1649, this man led armies which sacked Drogheda (pr. DRAH-huh-dah),\nleading to his reputation as a cruel conqueror of Ireland. He was succeeded by his son Richard\nafter his death. For 10 points, name this leader of the New Model Army who attained supreme\npower as \"Lord Protector of England\" after the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell, Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) What President of Germany, who appointed Hitler Chancellor in 1933, was the\nnamesake of a zeppelin that caught fire above New Jersey in 1937?",
      "answer": "Paul von Hindenburg, Hindenburg"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's reforms were sabotaged when Qi (pr. CHEE) sent dancing girls and horses to\ndistract the Duke of Lu. This man advocated the \"reification (pr. RAY-iff-uh-CAY-shun) of\nnames\" and the \"five relationships.\" For 10 points, name this author of the \"Five Classics\" whose\nsayings, collected in the Analects, form the basis of a traditional Chinese ruling philosophy.",
        "answer": "Confucius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Confucius lived during the Spring and Autumn period, in which what Chinese dynasty,\nnominally in power from 1046 to 256 BC, was in decline?",
        "answer": "Eastern Zhou, Zhou, Zhou Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this century, the Ottoman Empire's Tulip Period began with the Treaty of Passarowitz\n(pr. puh-SAH-roe-vits). At the end of this century, the White Lotus Rebellion broke out in\nChina. The Battle of Plassey and the Black Hole of Calcutta took place in this century. For 10\npoints, identify this century in which Britain took control of Canada after the French and Indian\nWar.",
        "answer": "18th, 18th century AD, 1700s, 1700"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Plassey weakened what Islamic dynasty that had ruled in India since\n1526, transferring effective control of most of India to the British East India Company?",
        "answer": "Mughal, Mughal Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alexander Neckham first described the European use of this object, which began in 1190 after\nit was invented in China. This object was used in conjunction with Portolan charts to double the\nVenetian trading season, which previously relied on clear skies for navigation. For 10 points,\nname this navigational device which uses the Earth's magnetic field to point north.",
        "answer": "compass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other great navigational problem was solved by John Harrison with the invention\nof the \"Sea Clock\" in 1730, winning a namesake twenty-thousand pound prize?",
        "answer": "longitude, determining a ship's longitude"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Ford administration declared this phenomenon \"public enemy number one\" and circulated\nbuttons which encouraged Americans to \"whip\" this thing \"now.\" Paul Volcker was instructed by\nthe Reagan administration to get this thing under control at any cost to the unemployment rate.\nFor 10 points, identify this phenomenon of generally rising prices.",
        "answer": "inflation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul Volcker was the chairman of what body, a position later held by Alan Greenspan?",
        "answer": "Federal Reserve, The Fed, Fed, Board of Governors, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state's Jackson County is where the Garden of Eden was located in Mormon belief. This\nstate was added to the U.S. as a slave state in exchange for Maine coming in as a free state, in its\nnamesake \"compromise.\" For 10 points, name this state that shares its name with the longest\nriver in the USA, which meets the Mississippi River here near the Gateway Arch in St. Louis.",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Missouri city of Independence was the start of what route, which settlers took to\nreach the Willamette Valley?",
        "answer": "Oregon Trail"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man first came to prominence by suppressing the 13 Vendémiaire (pr. VON-deem-yair)\nrebellion with what Thomas Carlyle called \"a whiff of grapeshot.\" He made his brothers Joseph\nand Jerome into the kings of Spain and Westphalia, respectively. For 10 points, name this \"First\nCounsel\" who was defeated by the Duke of Wellington at Waterloo.",
        "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte, Napoleon, Napoleon I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon was able to remove Austria and the Holy Roman Empire from the Third\nCoalition opposing him with what great 1805 victory in what is now the Czech Republic?",
        "answer": "Austerlitz, Battle of Austerlitz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A scandal leading up to this ballot question involved abusive Twitter messages sent to J.K.\nRowling. Alistair Darling appeared in an August 2014 debate on behalf of Better Together,\nwhich led the \"no\" campaign on this question. For 10 points, identify this September 2014 ballot\nquestion which sought to make Edinburgh the capital of a new sovereign country.",
        "answer": "Scottish independence, Scottish independence referendum"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which largest Scottish city by population was one of the few areas where the majority\nof people voted for independence?",
        "answer": "Glasgow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Troops who carried out this action referred to it as “Blumenkrieg”, a term meaning \"war of\nflowers,\" because they were met by cheering crowds. Kurt Schuschnigg (pr. SHOOS-neg) was\nforced to resign to clear the way for this action, which began on March 11, 1938. For 10 points,\nidentify this forced incorporation of Austria into Nazi Germany.",
        "answer": "Anschluss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Austria was forbidden from unifying with Germany by the Treaty of Saint-Germain\n(pr. sahn zhair-MON), which was signed at the end of what war?",
        "answer": "World War I, First World War, the Great War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"foundations\" of this field were described in a book by David Hilbert, and its \"hyperbolic\"\nform was pioneered by János Bolyai (pr. YAH-nowsh BOWL-yai) and the Russian Nikolai\nLobachevsky (pr. LOH-buh-CHEFF-skee). For 10 points, name this math field whose\nfoundational text is the Elements by Euclid (pr. YOOK-lid), which discusses the parallel\npostulate and Pythagorean theorem.",
        "answer": "geometry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other kind of mathematics was invented simultaneously by Gottfried Leibniz and\nIsaac Newton, who long quarreled over the credit for its discovery?",
        "answer": "calculus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist depicted Nazi concentration camp victims in The Charnel House. In the late 1940s,\nthis wealthy artist was the primary financial backer of the French Communist Party. An earlier\npolitical painting by him shows a lightbulb, a horse, and a screaming woman in memory of a\nBasque village bombed by the Nazis. For 10 points, name this creator of Guernica.",
        "answer": "Pablo Picasso, Picasso, Pablo Ruiz y Picasso"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "World War II itself caused the disappearance of many artworks, such as the Amber\nRoom formerly found in what city, which was besieged by Nazis for nine hundred days?",
        "answer": "St. Petersburg, Leningrad"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s former troops revolted against it in the Mercenary War. As a result, this city's\nleader Hanno the Great was displaced by the rising Barcid dynasty, whose members included\nHamilcar and Hasdrubal. This city lost the Battle of Zama to Scipio Africanus. For 10 points\nname this ancient North African city which was defeated by Rome in three Punic Wars.",
        "answer": "Carthage"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The site of Carthage is in which present day African country, whose soccer team is\nthus known as the Carthage Eagles?",
        "answer": "Tunisia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "San Francisco 49ers, San Francisco, 49ers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1950s, this team was led by quarterback Y.A. Tittle and the \"Million Dollar Backfield.\"\nThis team's receiver Dwight Clark made \"The Catch\" in 1982, and in January 1995, with\nquarterback Steve Young, they became the first NFL team to win a fifth Super Bowl. For 10\npoints, name this team that won four titles under the leadership of Joe Montana.",
        "answer": "Jerry Rice, Rice"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Soon after independence, this country fell under the domination of the \"hairy feet\" secret\npolice of José de Francia. This country was ruled by the eccentric Francisco Solano Lopez when\nit lost the majority of its male population to the War of the Triple Alliance. For 10 points,\nidentify this country which has developed oddly due to its landlocked position in South America.",
        "answer": "Paraguay, Republic of Paraguay, Republica del Paraguay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of the Triple Alliance proved a victory for Pedro II, a member of the\nBraganza Dynasty and the last person to hold what imperial title?",
        "answer": "Emperor of Brazil"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A powerful official in this government was the \"censor,\" who determined eligibility for the\nSenate. Politicians under this government followed the \"cursus honorum\" to move through the\nranks of aedile (pr. EY-dial), quaestor (pr. KWAI-stor), praetor (pr. PRAI-tor), and finally\nbecome one of two consuls. For 10 points, name this governmental system which was replaced\nby the Empire.",
        "answer": "Roman Republic, Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A legendary censor was the \"elder\" man of what name, who was also known for ending\nhis speeches in the Senate by declaring \"Carthage must be destroyed?\"",
        "answer": "Cato"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A bronze age museum is maintained at a \"crannog\" in County Clare on this island. This island\nregained its independence from Viking kingdoms at the 1014 Battle of Clontarf, re-establishing\nthe High King's seat at the hill of Tara. The Book of Kells can be seen at Trinity College Library\non this island. For 10 points, name this island, also home to the James Joyce Museum in Dublin.",
        "answer": "Ireland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What city in southwest Ireland is the namesake of a humorous poetic form?",
        "answer": "Limerick"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A desire to control this site sparked a brief 1860s war between France and Siam. This complex\nwas built by Suryavarman II (pr. SIR-yuh-VAHR-mun the second) in the early twelfth century\nand dedicated to Vishnu, though it was later used for Buddhist worship. For 10 points, identify\nthis Khmer (pr. kuh-MARE) Kingdom temple complex, or \"wat,\" in what is now Cambodia.",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat, Angkor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cambodia later came under the rule of the Khmer Rouge, a Communist movement led\nby what dictator whose original name was Saloth Sar?",
        "answer": "Pol Pot"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FAMOUS GREEKS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "What person or god from ancient Greece…\nWas the leader of the Olympian gods and was depicted in a famous statue at Olympia?",
          "answer": "Zeus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran naked through the streets of Syracuse shouting \"Eureka\" after discovering buoyancy?",
          "answer": "Archimedes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led a cult which opposed eating beans and discovered a side length theorem for right\ntriangles?",
          "answer": "Pythagoras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the \"gadfly of Athens\" whose Apology was recorded by Plato?",
          "answer": "Socrates"
        },
        {
          "question": "Offered a salt spring as a gift to Athens, which then chose Athena as its patron deity instead?",
          "answer": "Poseidon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the first book of history, The Persian Wars?",
          "answer": "Herodotus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was called the \"tenth muse\" for her accomplishments as a female poet on Lesbos?",
          "answer": "Sappho"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave a \"funeral oration\" on Athenian ideals during the Peloponnesian War?",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MEDIEVAL EASTERN EUROPE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "In the Middle Ages, who or what was the…\nEmpire which, by the 1070s, was reduced to the area around Constantinople?",
          "answer": "Byzantine, Byzantine Empire, Eastern Roman Empire, Eastern Roman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country first organized by the Piast Dynasty, which was later invaded by its neighbor\nGermany to start World War II?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim empire based in Turkey which conquered much of the region from 1308 to 1571?",
          "answer": "Ottoman, Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country where the Grand Duchy of Muscovy formed around the city of Moscow?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group which briefly overran Eastern Europe after defeating the Hungarians at Mohi in 1241?",
          "answer": "Mongol, Mongols"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Vladimir the Great converted a namesake state to Christianity before it became the\nUkrainian capital?",
          "answer": "Kiev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince of Wallachia (pr. wah-LAY-kee-uh) whose practice of putting opposing soldiers on\nstakes inspired vampire legends?",
          "answer": "Vlad the Impaler, Vlad Dracula, Dracula, Vlad III, Vlad Tepes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle, which shares its name with a Balkan country that declared independence in 2008 from\nSerbia?",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HERBERT HOOVER",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Name the person or event from the life or presidency of Hoover that was...\nThe four-term New Deal architect who succeeded him",
          "answer": "Franklin Delano Roosevelt, F Roosevelt, FDR"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Chicago mob kingpin convicted of tax evasion",
          "answer": "Al Capone, Capone, Alphonse Gabriel Capone"
        },
        {
          "question": "His \"Silent\" predecessor in the White House",
          "answer": "Calvin Coolidge, Coolidge, John Calvin Coolidge"
        },
        {
          "question": "The East Asian language he spoke, along with more native speakers than any other language",
          "answer": "Chinese, Mandarin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The prestigious California university which he attended in its first year",
          "answer": "Stanford, Stanford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "The popular nickname for the stock market crash of October 29, 1929",
          "answer": "Black Tuesday"
        },
        {
          "question": "The disastrous 1930 tariff bill which worsened the Depression",
          "answer": "Smoot-Hawley Tariff, Smoot-Hawley, Hawley-Smoot, Hawley-Smoot Tariff"
        },
        {
          "question": "A group of World War I veterans who marched on Washington",
          "answer": "Bonus Army"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "RECONSTRUCTION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "During the post-Civil War Reconstruction period in the U.S., who or what was the…\nState that took a long time to recover from Sherman’s March from Atlanta to Savannah?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hood-wearing group of Southern vigilantes which violently opposed black political power?",
          "answer": "KKK, Ku Klux Klan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Derogatory term given by Southerners to Northerners who moved South?",
          "answer": "carpetbaggers, carpetbagger"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was impeached during the Reconstruction Era?",
          "answer": "Andrew Johnson, A Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment which prohibited slavery throughout the United States?",
          "answer": "Thirteenth Amendment, Thirteenth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two-word name given to the dominant faction in Congress which drove Reconstruction?",
          "answer": "Radical Republicans, Radical Republican"
        },
        {
          "question": "Long-unenforced Constitutional amendment barring racial discrimination in voting?",
          "answer": "Fifteenth Amendment, Fifteenth"
        },
        {
          "question": "President whose inauguration ended Reconstruction as part of the Compromise of 1877?",
          "answer": "Rutherford B. Hayes, Hayes, Rutherford Birchard Hayes"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CHARLEMAGNE",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Medieval emperor Charlemagne…\nWas crowned on Christmas 800 by Leo III, a holder of what top office of the Catholic\nChurch?",
          "answer": "Pope, the Papacy, Papacy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Instigated the \"Carolingian\" example of what sort of period in which arts and learning revive?",
          "answer": "renaissance"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched a crusade against what Germanic people, who earlier joined with the Angles to\nconquer England?",
          "answer": "Saxons, Saxon"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 797, took control of what currently second largest city in Spain?",
          "answer": "Barcelona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the son of what small-statured king?",
          "answer": "Pepin the Short, Pepin III, Pepin le Bref, Pippin der Kurze"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was gifted what kind of large animal, known as Abul-Abbas, by the Abbasid caliph?",
          "answer": "elephant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of which Germanic tribe who were earlier led by the Merovingians?",
          "answer": "Franks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the grandson of what Mayor of the Palace who won the Battle of Tours?",
          "answer": "Charles Martel, Carolus Martellus, Karl Martell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE PHILIPPINES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The present-day country of the Philippines is or was…\nColonized by what European power, after whose king Philip II it was named?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controlled from an 1898 war until independence by what country?",
          "answer": "United States of America, USA, America"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to the Moro people and Abu Sayyaf (pr. sai-AHF) movement, which follow what\nminority religion?",
          "answer": "Sunni Islam, Muslim, Muslims"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the Battle of Leyte (pr. LAY-tee) Gulf during which war?",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Subject to the “New Society” regime of what dictator from 1965 to 1986?",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to thousands of what item of clothing that belonged to that man's wife Imelda?",
          "answer": "shoes"
        },
        {
          "question": "The destination of galleons that left the port of Acapulco from which country in the Americas?",
          "answer": "Mexico"
        },
        {
          "question": "Briefly led as president by what independence activist who led an anti-American insurgency\nuntil 1901?",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo, Aguinaldo"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The use of this three word phrase ended a secret program by which Ryan Crocker coordinated the capture of Al-Qaeda operatives. This phrase originally ended with the word \"hatred\" when David Frum wrote it into a section of the ",
        "(20 pts) 2002 State of the Union Address that argued for the overthrow of Saddam Hussein. ",
        "(10 pts) For 10 points, give this threeword phrase used by George W. Bush to describe Iraq, Iran, and North Korea by analogy to an earlier grouping of Germany, Italy, and Japan."
      ],
      "answer": "axis of evil"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A major book about these places was based heavily on the recollections of Georg Tenno. These places were initially described only in \"samizdat\" literature, whose ",
        "(20 pts) possession could get a person sent to these places, which were the subject of the ",
        "(10 pts) Kolyma Tales. For 10 points, name these places whose \"archipelago\" is the subject of a book by Alexander Solzhenitsyn, who also set One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich in one of these forced Soviet labor camps."
      ],
      "answer": "gulag, gulags"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this era, Josquin des Prez (pr. JOHS-kin day PRAY) made advances in polyphony (puh-LIFF-uh-nee), and Giovanni da Palestrina wrote the ",
        "(20 pts) Pope Marcellus Mass. This era's music came under fire at the Council of Trent and was succeeded by the ",
        "(10 pts) Baroque period. For 10 points, identify this period in Western musical history in which motets and masses were the dominant form of music, and which shares its name with a \"rebirth\" in literature and visual arts."
      ],
      "answer": "the Renaissance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This substance was the subject of the \"Letter to Queen Victoria\" sent by Commissioner Lin, who burned chests full of it on the beach. This substance was mixed with alcohol to make the eighteenth-century medicine ",
        "(20 pts) \"laudanum\" and was consumed in namesake \"dens.\" The seizure of the Arrow sparked a second ",
        "(10 pts) war named for this substance. For 10 points, identify this narcotic whose first war ended when the Treaty of Nanking granted European concessions in China."
      ],
      "answer": "opium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Herbert Fairbank first explained the potential for this system in 1939 after expanding the Pershing Map. This system was authorized by a 1956 law but not completed until 1992, at a cost of 114 ",
        "(20 pts) billion dollars. This system was championed by Dwight Eisenhower, who had seen the uses of the ",
        "(10 pts) Autobahn system while serving in Germany. For 10 points, identify this road network which includes even-numbered east-west routes and odd-numbered north-south routes."
      ],
      "answer": "Interstate, Interstate Highway System, interstate highways"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Russell S. Penniman found a cheaper way to make this product, which must be periodically rotated to avoid the pooling of its active component out of the ",
        "(20 pts) sawdust medium. This product reduced the danger of using black powder or unmodified ",
        "(10 pts) nitroglycerin, and led to its inventor being dubbed \"the merchant of death.\" For 10 points, identify this explosive with mining and military applications, which requires a blasting cap and was devised by Alfred Nobel."
      ],
      "answer": "dynamite"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger Ascham described the use of this weapon in the manual Toxophilus, and it survived in the British army until World War II, when Jack Churchill killed a Nazi soldier with one of them. These weapons were sometimes named for the ",
        "(20 pts) Welsh people who invented them and perfected their use, and they were used to great effect by the English at ",
        "(10 pts) Agincourt (pr. AA-jin-core). For 10 points, name this six-foot-tall archery weapon which replaced the crossbow."
      ],
      "answer": "longbow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was aided by a 1946 enforcement of the Smoke Control Ordinance under David Lawrence. Factory workers in this city told of Joe Magerac and invented a method of cooking steak that produces a charred exterior and raw inside. This city was where ",
        "(20 pts) Pinkerton detectives were hired to break the Homestead strike by Henry Clay Frick and Andrew ",
        "(10 pts) Carnegie. For 10 points, name this former center of steel production, which is at the head of the Ohio River in Western Pennsylvania."
      ],
      "answer": "Pittsburgh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Because two million acres in this American state were set aside for veterans, the land became known as the \"Military Tract\" and towns there were named Pompey, Solon, and Scipio. This state's \"burned-over district\" was the center of the ",
        "(20 pts) Second Great Awakening, and its city of ",
        "(10 pts) Cooperstown became the home of the Baseball Hall of Fame due to an erroneous belief that the game was invented there. For 10 points, name this home of the Finger Lakes and Buffalo."
      ],
      "answer": "New York"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Buffalo Springfield insisted that the song \"For What It's Worth\" was about the Sunset Strip curfew riots and not this event. This event was the subject of Country Joe and the Fish's biggest hit. A veteran of this conflict is the subject of ",
        "(20 pts) Bruce Springsteen's \"Born in the USA,\" and a ",
        "(10 pts) protest against this conflict inspired Neil Young to write \"Ohio\" about the Kent State shootings. For 10 points, name this war which inspired copious protest music in the late 1960s."
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam War, Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1844, the U.S. dispatched missionary Peter Parker and attorney Caleb Cushing to this country to negotiate a trade pact. This country signed the 1868 Burlingame Treaty with the United States. This country's natives were the subject of the ",
        "(20 pts) Geary Act, and were prohibited from entering the U.S. between 1882 and 1943 under a namesake ",
        "(10 pts) \"Exclusion Act.\" For 10 points, name this country which is now, after Canada, the second-largest trade partner of the U.S."
      ],
      "answer": "China, People's Republic of China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An important 1878 piece for this instrument was composed for the virtuoso Joseph Joachim (pr. YO-zef YO-ah-keem). This instrument was played by a composer of ",
        "(20 pts) twenty-four caprices who allegedly made a deal with the devil, Niccolò ",
        "(10 pts) Paganini. Many valuable examples of this instrument were created by the master craftsman Antonio Stradivari. For 10 points, name this string instrument which an orchestra's concertmaster plays."
      ],
      "answer": "violin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization was formed at the suggestion of Mary White Ovington following the Springfield riot of 1908, and it absorbed many veterans of the Niagara Movement. This organization awards the ",
        "(20 pts) Spingarn Medals, and its first major effort was publishing The Crisis under the editorship of ",
        "(10 pts) W.E.B. DuBois (pr. doo-BOYZ). For 10 points, name this organization which led the anti-segregationist movement for much of the twentieth century."
      ],
      "answer": "NAACP, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man won a Nobel Prize in Literature for his History of the English-Speaking Peoples. This man was First Lord of the Admiralty during the ",
        "(20 pts) Gallipoli disaster, though his \"wilderness years\" eventually ended and allowed him to make the \"we shall ",
        "(10 pts) fight them on the beaches\" speech. He was defeated in his first re-election bid by Clement Attlee. For 10 points, name this leader of the national unity government of the U.K. during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Winston Churchill, Churchill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this organization were represented in the Reichstag by the Centre Party. This organization was targeted by Adalbert von Falk's May Laws, part of the ",
        "(20 pts) Kulturkampf (pr. KOOL-tur-kompf) against it launched by Otto von Bismarck. A leader of this organization who was accused of turning a blind eye to the Holocaust was ",
        "(10 pts) Pius XII. For 10 points, name this organization which is the predominant Christian denomination in southern Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church, Catholic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) People who opposed this action wrote under the pen names Cato, Brutus, and the Federal Farmer, and were most likely George Clinton, Robert Yates, and Mercy Otis Warren. This action was supported in a series of ",
        "(20 pts) letters to the New York Packet written by \"Publius,\" a collective pseudonym for James ",
        "(10 pts) Madison, John Jay, and Alexander Hamilton. For 10 points, what was this action which was advocated in the Federalist Papers and created the present U.S. government?"
      ],
      "answer": "ratifying the U.S. Constitution, ratifying Constitution"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first-ever U.S. Cabinet member to serve a prison sentence did so as a result of this scandal. This scandal's investigation by Thomas Walsh led to the Supreme Court case of McGrain v. Daugherty, which held that Congress may require people to testify. It involved ",
        "(20 pts) land in the Black Hills which Albert Fall, the Secretary of the Interior, leased to ",
        "(10 pts) oil prospectors at cut rates. For 10 points, identify this defining scandal of the Warren Harding administration."
      ],
      "answer": "Teapot Dome"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This city was the site of a Church council held five years before the Council of Constance which elected Alexander V as Pope in an attempt to end the Western Schism. This city was the loser of the Battle of ",
        "(20 pts) Meloria, and it was where a man allegedly dropped ",
        "(10 pts) cannonballs out of a window in order to measure acceleration. For 10 points, name this home to a gravitational experiment by Galileo, who made use of an architectural blunder that created its \"leaning tower.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Pisa"
    }
  ]
}
